J. Harry DuBois Papers
J. Harry DuBois Papers
1940-1993
DuBois, J. Harry (John Harry), 1903-
4 linear ft.
Collection consists of the personal and professional papers of J. Harry DuBois, covering his long career in the plastics industry. It includes scrapbooks and photograph albums of his family and world-wide travel for business, photographs and slides, and audio and film reels.
2651115
Biographical History
J. Harry DuBois (1903-1986) was an American businessman and author in the field of plastics.
Born September 18, 1903 in Clarion, Iowa, he began at General Electric Co.'s molding division in 1927. In 1944, he moved to Shaw Insulator Co. until 1950 when he left to work at Plax Corporation where he stayed through 1951. DuBois was vice president of Mycalex Corporation of America from 1952 to 1958 and vice president of Tech Art Plastics from 1960 to 1965. He founded J. Harry DuBois Co. in 1958, serving as as plastics consultant. In 1965, DuBois became president of Molecular Dielectrics, Inc. and president of Mykroy Ceramics Corporation in 1972.
DuBois was also an author and lecturer. His first book, Plastics, published in 1942 and now in its fifth edition, continues to be the basic text and reference book for schools, colleges, and in-plant training programs. Other works include Plastics Mold Engineering and Plastics History U.S.A. He was inducted into the Plastics Hall of Fame in 1973. DuBois died in March of 1986.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The J. Harry DuBois Papers consists of the personal and professional papers of J. Harry DuBois, covering his long career in the plastics industry, divided into papers, scrapbooks and photo albums, photographs, and audio and film material.
Papers contains personal and professional papers: a Society of Plastics Engineers International Award in Plastics; consolidated financial statement of Molecular Dielectrics from 1969; Mykroy Ceramics price book from 1974 and Mykroy informational kit; and papers related to the restoration of the Marshalltown, Iowa courthouse in 1977. It also includes cards from his rolodex and business cards he collected over the years.
Scrapbooks & photo albums, 1940s-1993, contains eight scrapbooks and photo albums documenting family world travel and DuBois’ career in plastics including his induction into the Plastics Hall of Fame. Locations include Dusseldorf, Scandinavia, India and the Orient. (Two scrapbooks were removed from their housing: Misc. 1958-1977 and Scandinavian Tour 1976.)
Photographs consists of prints and slides. Prints includes a copy print of the DuBoises with President Gerald Ford, Willerts, Islyn Thomas (2003.865), four prints removed from Molecular Dielectrics Financial Statement, Helen DuBois as child, DuBois accepting his Plastics Hall of Fame award, and photographs of his family. Slides include buildings/building materials, charts/diagrams, family/personal, machinery/manufacturing, molds/molding, objects, parts and people.
Audio and film formats include reel-to-reel audio, films, and audiocassettes. Topics include Bakelite, Plastics Pioneers, Mycalex, and the Lima, Peru manufacturing plant.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is divided into the series listed above, but otherwise is in no particular order.
Related Material
has numerous holdings in the areas of plastics and industrial design. Please refer to for a complete listing. See in particular the
Wayne I. Pribble Papers
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Plastics; DuBois, J. Harry (John Harry), 1903-; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006.; Molecular Dielectrics, Inc.; Plastics Hall of Fame.; Bakelite -- History.; Industrialization -- India.; Plastics industry and trade.; Düsseldorf (Germany); Marshalltown (Iowa); Audiotapes.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Negatives (photographs); Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Slides (photographs); Businessmen.; Industrialists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from National Plastics Center and Museum, 11/06/2008. Originally, gift of DuBois family.
Inventory
- Papers
  - Address book, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Business cards, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Financial and business, 1970; 1972 (Box 1)
    Items include: Molecular Dielectrics, Inc. and Subsidiary Companies consolidated financial statements as of December 31, 1969, together with auditors’ report, 1970 (2 copies); Mykroy Ceramics Corporation bound information booklet, 1972.
  - Mckroy ceramics price book, 1974 (Box 1)
  - Personal and professional, 1944-1984 (Box 1)
    Items include Postcard; Letter from James L. Thronere: presentation at ANTEC ’83; European travel log, Sept. 1956; Letter to G. R. Munger; Letter from Andrea DiNoto; Letter to James Edwards Book; Letter to Mort Gilbert; Communications re: Pavia Farny Corp.; Plax Corp. Pioneers Newsletter, 1983; Communications re: first all plastics airplane; Letter to Francis Fu; Letter from Industry Media Inc.; Newspaper and magazine clippings; Letter from National Museum of American History; Communications with Wayne Pribble; Toolmaker lunch trade publication; Certificates from Pittsfield University, University of Minnesota; Plastics Pioneers Association, The Society of Plastics Industry, United States Navy.
  - Restoration of Marshalltown courthouse, 1977; contains communications, newspaper clippings, and draft manuscripts related to the restoration of the Marshalltown Courthouse in Marshalltown, Iowa (Box 1)
  - SPE international award in plastics, 1966-1967; 1977; includes personal communications, press releases, trade publication clippings, reprints of Plastics World March 1966 article, nominating forms (Box 1)
  - Wedding invitation, 1973 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Negatives, circa 1970s; assorted negatives including: Pioneers of Plastic, 1980; National Plastics Museum; Plax Corporation party; Mykroy (1972); Pioneers in Plastic (Sept 1974); Pioneers of Plastic (1973); Seminar at Hyatt in Cherry Hill; assorted objects; injection molds; Hull press; Chicago seminar Xmas 1978 (Box 1)
  - Prints, 1944-1979; 2 folders; assortment of photographs including: Mycalex party; accepting Hall of Fame Award; daguerreotype; comb; daguerreotype in case; daguerreotype cases; 19th century molding machine; plastics pioneer; family and friends; “Levy”; Schwrenfiest, Germany; fiber optic; tech art annex; conference; DuBois and Mario Petretti (1949); DuBois (1949); DuBois portrait; Molecular Dielectrics (1969); “Pig” of synthetamica; instrument used in making synthamica; Helen DuBois (1944); DuBois portrait (1944?); DuBois speaking; machinery parts or molds; gravestones (Box 1)
  - Slides, undated; miscellaneous photographs of family and friends (Box 2)
  - Slides, undated; miscellaneous slides of buildings/building materials; charts/diagrams; family/personal (Japan and Dusseldorf trips); machinery/manufacturing; molds/molding; objects; parts; people (Oversize 2)
- Scrapbooks and photo albums
  - Advisory committee for industrialization of India, 1986; Assorted notes and communications (Oversize 3)
  - Dusseldorf, Germany, 1986; assortment of photographs and postcards (Box 2)
  - Family, friends, work, undated; assorted photographs (Box 2)
  - Japan trip, 1971; assorted photographs and postcards, and a typed travel log. The trip included visits to: Nissei Plant; Tokyo Kasei Industries, Ltd.; Dai-I Chi Seiki Co., Ltd.; Philco Ford Plant; Kader Industrial Co., Ltd.; H. Cheong Leen & Co.; Dow Chemical (Oversize 3)
  - Plastics Hall of Fame induction, 1973; assorted photographs, communications (e.g., nomination, notification, and congratulatory letters), speeches, newspaper clippings, invitations, and program related to DuBois' induction into The Plastics Hall of Fame in 1973. Also includes the October 1973 issue of Modern Plastics, which has biographies of all inductees. 1973 was the inaugural induction ceremony (Oversize 4)
  - Scandinavian tour, 1976; assorted photographs and postcards, and a typed travel log (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1958-1977; includes DuBois' resume, newspaper clippings and press releases relating to the preservation of tombstones and artifacts, and a telephone book (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; collection, primarily of photographs, from DuBois' adult life; also includes his newspaper and other obituaries (Oversize 5)
- Audio & film
  - Reel to reel audio
    - "1952 Plastics Pioneers", dubois_009; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - "Bakelite, Boonton Molding, welding molds, red germ resin, etc.", dubois_014; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - "Bill Cruse and Lou Francisco, D.J. O’Conor part 1 and 2", dubois_008; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - "Plastics Pioneers" Reel 1, dubois_010; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - "Plastics Pioneers" Reel 2, dubois_011; 1 audio reel; "Side A: Garson Meyers (Kodak), Fred C. Meacham (Nic), Herb Spencer (Durez), Hans Wanders (Nic); Side B: M.M. Makeever, C.A. Norris Jr., G.V. Sammet, B.E. Schlesinger" (Oversize 6)
    - "Red Brommer, Gorde Brow", dubois_012; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - Untitled, dubois_006; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - Untitled, dubois_007; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
    - Untitled, dubois_013; 1 audio reel (Oversize 6)
  - Films
    - "Mycalex, 1954-1955", dubois_004; 1 film reel (Oversize 6)
    - Untitled, dubois_005; 1 film reel (Oversize 6)
  - Audio cassettes
    - "Liberty machine, Lima Peru plant", dubois_002; 1 audio cassette (Oversize 6)
    - World Research presents: "Not yours to give", dubois_001; 1 audio cassette (Oversize 6)
    - Untitled, dubois_003; 1 audio cassette (Oversize 6)